Guide to the Peter Safar Papers, 1950-2003 UA.90.F102
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Publications, IV.
  - Journal Articles, 1.
    This subseries contains journal articles that were published by Peter Safar. They are organized by the year of publication.
    - Publications, 1955 (Box 23, Folder 17)
    - Publications, 1958 (Box 23, Folder 18)
    - Publications, 1959 (Box 23, Folder 19)
    - Publications, 1961 (Box 23, Folder 20)
    - Publications, 1965 (Box 23, Folder 21)
    - Publications, 1966 (Box 23, Folder 22)
    - Publications, 1967 (Box 23, Folder 23)
    - Publications, 1968 (Box 23, Folder 24)
    - Publications, 1969 (Box 23, Folder 25)
    - Publications, 1970 (Box 23, Folder 26)
    - Publications, 1971 (Box 23, Folder 27)
    - Publications, 1972 (Box 23, Folder 28)
    - Publications, 1973 (Box 23, Folder 29)
    - Publications, 1974 (Box 23, Folder 30)
    - Publications, 1975 (Box 23, Folder 31)
    - Publications, 1976 (Box 23, Folder 32)
    - Publications, 1977 (Box 23, Folder 33)
    - Publications, 1978 (Box 23, Folder 34)
    - Publications, 1979 (Box 23, Folder 35)
    - Publications, 1980 (Box 23, Folder 36)
    - Publications, 1981 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Publications, 1982 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Publications, 1983 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Publications, 1984 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Publications, 1985 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Publications, 1986 (Box 24, Folder 6-8)
    - Publications, 1987 (Box 24, Folder 9)
    - Publications, 1988 (Box 24, Folder 10)
    - Publications, 1989 (Box 24, Folder 11)
    - Publications, 1990 (Box 24, Folder 12)
    - Publications, 1991 (Box 24, Folder 13-14)
    - Publications, 1992 (Box 24, Folder 15)
    - Publications, 1993 (Box 24, Folder 16)
    - Publications, 1994 (Box 24, Folder 17)
    - Publications, 1995 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Publications, 1996 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Publications, 1997 (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Publications, 1998 (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Publications, 1999 (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Publications, 2000 (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - Publications, 2001 (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - Publications, 2002 (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - Publications, 2003 (Box 25, Folder 9)
  - Manuals and Reports, 2.
    This subseries contains manuals and reports contributed to or written by Peter Safar. The manual entitled Cardio-Pulmonary Cerebral Reanimation is a Spanish translation of a Safar work.
    - Emergency Care in the Field, A Manual for Paramedics, Introduction-Chapter 5, 1975 (Box 25, Folder 10)
    - Emergency Care in the Field, A Manual for Paramedics, Chapters 6-11, 1975 (Box 25, Folder 11)
    - Emergency Care in the Field, A Manual for Paramedics, Chapter 12-Glossary, 1975 (Box 25, Folder 12)
    - Cardio-Pulmonary Cerebral Reanimation, Introduction- Chapter 1b, 1981 (Box 25, Folder 13)
    - Cardio-Pulmonary Cerebral Reanimation, Chapter 1c- 3, 1981 (Box 25, Folder 14)
    - Cardio-Pulmonary Cerebral Reanimation, Chapter 4- Conclusion, 1981 (Box 25, Folder 15)
  - Research, 3.
    This subseries contains the research conducted by Peter Safar for various projects.
    - Blood Transfusion Papers/Articles, 1984-1997 (Box 25, Folder 16)
    - Combat Related Trauma Papers/Surveys (Box 25, Folder 17)
    - Combat Related Trauma Papers/Surveys, World War I Related (Box 25, Folder 18)
    - Combat Related Trauma Papers/Surveys, World War II Related (Box 25, Folder 19-20)
    - Key Figures in Trauma Care Papers, 1984-1997 (Box 25, Folder 21)
    - Pittsburgh Post-Gazette Article on Martin Luther King, 1993 (Box 25, Folder 22)
    - Research for Trauma, 2000 (Box 26, Folder 1-9)
    - Tetanus Papers, 1966-1977 (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - Trauma Papers, 1991-2003 (Box 26, Folder 11)
- Biography and Legacy, V.
  This series includes files regarding the legacy of Peter Safar, as well as biographies written about him. It also includes a scrapbook and information about Safar's time in Baltimore and his work on the creation of the ABC's of CPR. The contents of Peter Safar's briefcase and information regarding his memorialization are also included within this series.
  - Biographies, 1.
    This subseries contains biographical sketches of Peter Safar used in publications, conferences and lectures. Other files pertain to articles, documentaries and other recognitions of Safar's contributions to medicine.
    - Allegheny General Hospital, Safar Biographical Sketch (Box 26, Folder 12)
    - American Biographical Institute Biographical Sketch, 1999 (Box 26, Folder 13)
    - Anesthesiology International Site Review, 1999 (Box 26, Folder 14)
    - Anesthesiology News, Safar Spotlight, 2002 (Box 26, Folder 15)
    - American Society of Anesthesiology Annual Meeting News, Lewis H. Wright Memorial Lecture, 2000 (Box 26, Folder 16)
    - American Society of Anesthesiology News Release on Suspended Animation, 2001 (Box 26, Folder 17)
    - Baskett Citation, 1994 (Box 26, Folder 18)
    - Baskett, Resuscitation Greats, 2001-2002 (Box 26, Folder 19)
    - Christer Grenvick Memorial Award, San Diego, 1989-1997 (Box 26, Folder 20)
    - Dickson Prize in Medicine and Mellon Prize, 1982-2002 (Box 26, Folder 21)
    - Emergency Article by K. Benson, 1992 (Box 26, Folder 22)
    - Finestone Review of American Society of Anesthesiologists Memoirs, 2001 (Box 26, Folder 23)
    - Freedom House Documentary News and Correspondence, 2001 (Box 26, Folder 24)
    - Hans Dahll Award, Montgomery Introduction, 1994 (Box 26, Folder 25)
    - Holmstrom Lecture Biography (Box 26, Folder 26)
    - Johns Hopkins 40 Year Celebration Dinner Talk, 2000 (Box 26, Folder 27)
    - Johns Hopkins Scholars Society (Box 26, Folder 28)
    - National Institute of Health Biographical Sketch (Box 26, Folder 29)
    - Nobel Prize Nomination, 1990 (Box 26, Folder 30)
    - Pitt Med Article, 1999 (Box 26, Folder 31)
    - Pittsburgh Health Care Heroes, 1996-1997 (Box 26, Folder 32)
    - Recommendation Letters, 1995-2003 (Box 26, Folder 33)
    - Robert White, Safar Santa Clause, 2001 (Box 26, Folder 34)
    - SCRR Ad Campaign Summary (Box 26, Folder 35)
    - Society of Critical Care Medicine Lifetime Achievement Award, 2002 (Box 26, Folder 36)
    - Wright Memorial Lecture Biographical Sketch, 2000 (Box 26, Folder 37)
  - Early Years, 2.
    This subseries contains information on the early years of Peter Safar's work. It includes lab notebooks, a guestbook for the Baltimore City Hospital, and a scrapbook of his work while developing CPR. The scrapbook contains newspaper clippings and photographs of CPR demonstrations on paralized volunteers, as well as emergency personnel performing CPR on patients in distress.
    - Lab Notebooks (Box 26, Folder 38)
    - Guestbook, 1960-1961 (Box 26, Folder 39)
    - Scrapbook (Box 27, Volume 1)
    - Awards From Scrapbook, 1958 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Photos from Scrapbook, Baltimore City Hospital (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Photos from Scrapbook, Baltimore Firefighters Performing Resuscitation, 1957 (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Photos from Scrapbook, Child Resuscitation (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence From Scrapbook (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Photos from Scrapbook, Emergency Kit (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Newspaper Clippings from Scrapbook, 1957-1958 (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - Newspaper Clippings from Scrapbook, 1958-1959 (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - Publications from Scrapbook, 1957-1958 (Box 30, Folder 9)
    - Photos from Scrapbook, Resuscitation (Box 30, Folder 10)
  - Awards and Plaques, 3.
    This subseries includes awards that Peter Safar received for his work from a variety of institutions, including the University of Pittsburgh and international medical organizations.
    - Allegheny County Medical Society Award, 1972 (Box 28, Item 1)
    - Freedom House Enterprise Inc. Award (Box 28, Item 2)
    - Graduates of the University of Pittsburgh Health Center Hospitals Award, 1972 (Box 28, Item 3)
    - Happy Boss Plaque, 1980 (Box 28, Item 4)
    - Honorary Member of Japan Society of Anesthesiology, 1992 (Box 28, Item 5)
    - Medical and Chirurgical Faculty of the State of Maryland Annual Meeting Award, 1983 (Box 28, Item 6)
    - Mount Sinai Hospital Bernard H. Eliasberg Lecture Award (Box 28, Item 7)
    - Pittsburgh Academy of Medicine Man of the Year Award, 1985 (Box 28, Item 8)
    - Pittsburgh-Allegheny County American Red Cross Award, 1988 (Box 28, Item 9)
    - American Board of Anesthesiology Certificate, 1957 (Box 29, Item 1)
    - Letter from President Bill Clinton, 1995 (Box 29, Item 2)
    - Medical License from Commonwealth of Pennsylvania State Board of Medical Education and Licensure, 1961 (Box 29, Item 3)
    - National Board of Medical Examiners Certificate, 1955 (Box 29, Item 4)
    - President Physician in Anesthesia at Hospital of the University of Pittsburgh Certificate, 1952 (Box 29, Item 5)
    - Society of Critical Care Medicine Founding Member Certificate, 1972 (Box 29, Item 6)
    - University of Pittsburgh Distinguished Professor Medal, 1978 (Box 29, Item 7)
    - Award of Outstanding Achievement from Deutsche Akademie der Naturforscher Leopoldina, 1987 (Box 30, Folder 11)
  - Memorial, 4.
    This subseries contains information and memorabilia regarding the legacy of Peter Safar. It includes a scrapbook of articles written about him after his death and pamphlets from the Safar Symposium and Lecture Series which was created in his memory. This subseries also includes a paper by Carnegie Mellon University student Andrew Simpson that was written about the work of Peter Safar.
    - Alliance of the Germanic Societies of Pittsburgh, Recognition Luncheon, 2014 (Box 30, Folder 12)
    - Award Ceremony Pamphlets, 1996-2004 (Box 30, Folder 13)
    - Memorial Articles, 2003 (Box 30, Folder 14)
    - Memorial Articles in Journals (Box 30, Folder 15-16)
    - Safar Symposium and Lecture Series (Box 30, Folder 17)
    - University of Pittsburgh Honors Convocation, 2003 (Box 30, Folder 18)
    - Transporting Lazarus: EMS Policy Making and Professionalization, Andrew T. Simpson, Carnegie Mellon University, 2009 (Box 30, Folder 19)
    - Memorial Articles Scrapbook, 2003 (Box 27, Volume 2)
  - Personal Effects, 5.
    This subseries contains the contents of Peter Safar's briefcase. All of the material within the briefcase has been grouped together and filed by topic.
    - Briefcase Contents, Conference Programs, 1951-1994 (Box 30, Folder 20)
    - Briefcase Contents, Department of Anesthesiology Documents, 1961-1980 (Box 30, Folder 21)
    - Briefcase Contents, Editions of Resuscitation Manuals and Surgery Book (Box 30, Folder 22)
    - Briefcase Contents, Publications, 1958-1996 (Box 30, Folder 23)
    - Briefcase Contents, Safar Curriculum Vitae (Box 30, Folder 24)
    - Briefcase (Box 30, Item 1)